{"tossups": [{"question": "This thinker claimed that human motivation was divided between <em>eros</em> and <em>thanatos</em>, or the life and death drives. This man divided the title constructs into manifest and latent content in his <em>The Interpretation of Dreams</em>. This thinker divided the unconscious into the ego, superego, and the id. Controversially claiming that young men develop an Oedipal [[ED-ih-\"pull\"]] complex, for ten points, which Austrian psychologist is considered the father of psychoanalysis?", "answer": "Sigmund <b><u>Freud</u></b> (or Sigismund Schlomo <b><u>Freud</u></b>)", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Psychology"}, {"question": "An island in this nation owned by naval officer William Owen was named by him Campobello in an effort to gain favor with the sitting royal governor, Lord William Campbell. The former mining town of Uranium City and many oil sands drilling sites are on the shore of this country's Lake Athabasca [[AH-thah-BAH-skah]]. In this nation, the SS <em>Mont</em> <em>Blanc's</em> collision with the SS <em>Imo</em> led to the deadly \"Halifax Explosion\" during the First World War. For ten points, name this North American country whose major cities include Ottawa and Montreal.", "answer": "<b><u>Canada</u></b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "The story of this opera was adapted for a 1998 musical of the same name with music by Elton John. An original \"potpourri\" overture was written for this opera, though it was cut from the 1871 premiere in Cairo. At the end of this opera, the title Ethiopian princess dies in the arms of her lover Radam\u00e8s [[rah-dah-MESS]], while priests sing hymns to Ptah. For ten points, name this four-act opera by Giuseppe Verdi about a romantic tragedy in the Old Kingdom of Egypt.", "answer": "<em><b><u>Aida</u></b></em>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Opera"}, {"question": "A 1942 movie musical titled for this song follows the life of George M. Cohan. The Marquis de Lafayette\u2019s band played this song as the British surrendered at Yorktown. In this song, the title character and his father \u201cwent down to Camp\u201d with Captain Gooding and saw \u201cmen and boys / As thick as hasty pudding.\u201d For ten points, name this song about an American who \u201cstuck a feather in his cap / And called it macaroni.\u201d", "answer": "\u201c<b><u>Yankee Doodle</u></b>\u201d (accept \"<b><u>Yankee Doodle Dandy</u></b>\")", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "In 1982, two laid-off Chrysler workers killed a man of this ethnic group in Highland Park, Michigan due to their anger at their company being outcompeted by the Japanese auto industry. This people group, who were killed en masse in the Rock Springs Massacre, experienced California's discriminatory Anti-Coolie Act. An 1882 \"Exclusion Act\" was passed to limit immigration by, for ten points, what Asian ethnic group, many of whom immigrated during the late Qing [[CHING]] Dynasty?", "answer": "<b><u>Chinese</u></b>-Americans (prompt on \"Asian\" or \"Asian-American\" before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Two students from this institution began the St. Scholastica Day Riot after being served poor quality wine. Rhodes Scholars are given full-rides to this university, which initially grew after Henry II banned his countrymen from attending the University of Paris. Following the 1209 lynching of two students from this institution, many scholars left to found its rival, Cambridge. For the point, name this university, the oldest in the English-speaking world.", "answer": "University of <b><u>Oxford</u></b> (accept <b><u>Oxford</u></b> University)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "One of these people was convicted in the case <em>Tuckiar v The King</em> after killing a police constable who assaulted the women of his tribe in Arnhem's Land. Turn-of-the-century laws in New South Wales and the Northern Territory allowed for the removal of the children of these people, collectively known as the Stolen Generations. In 1985, ownership of the site Uluru was given back to, for ten points, what indigenous people of Australia?", "answer": "<b><u>Aboriginal</u></b> Australians (or <b><u>Aborigines</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "American explorer Gene Savoy proved that this site and the legendary capital of Manco Yupanqui [[yoo-PAHN-kee]] Vilcabamba were distinct locales. A sun dial served as the centerpiece of this estate's Temple of Inti. This site, whose name translates to \"old peak\" in Quechua [[KEH-chwah]], likely served as the private estate of the <em>Sapa</em> Pachacuti. Hiram Bingham discovered, for ten points, what Incan citadel in the Andes of modern Peru?", "answer": "<b><u>Machu Picchu</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "A \"Cantata\" named for this river was written to commemorate a heroic last stand by fishermen near its Hukou [[HOO-KOO]] Waterfall. With Hou Ji [[HOH-JEE]], the semi-mythical Emperor Yu the Great stopped this river from flooding by using self-expanding soil called <em>Xirang</em> [[ZHEE-RAHNG]]. The Sui [[SWEE]] Dynasty began the construction of the Grand Canal, connecting this river and the Yangtze River. For the point, name this \"Mother River\" of China, named for the color of its muddy water.", "answer": "<b><u>Yellow</u></b> River (or <b><u>Hu\u00e1ng</u></b> h\u00e9 [[HWAHNG HUH]])", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "A mayor in this nation, Arturas Zuokas [[zoo-OH-kuss]], fought illegal parking in his city by crushing a car with an armored vehicle in 2011. This nation's language was preserved through the 19th-century \"Book Smuggling\" movement after Tsarist Russia banned its use. This modern state merged with a southern neighbor in the Union of Lublin, and it joined Estonia and Latvia in the anti-Soviet Singing Revolution. For ten points, name this Baltic state that formed a historical Commonwealth with Poland.", "answer": "Republic of <b><u>Lithuania</u></b> (accept Grandy Duchy of <b><u>Lithuania</u></b>; or <b><u>Lietuvos</u> </b>Respublika; or <b><u>Lietuva</u></b>; accept Polish-<b><u>Lithuania</u></b>n Commonwealth; accept Kingdom of Poland and the Grand Duchy of <b><u>Lithuania</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "In his writing, Alexis de Tocqueville [[TOKE-vil]] called this practice \"alien\" to the United States, and it first began in the Confederacy in 1862. This practice led to the phrase \"A rich man's war and a poor man's fight.\" A massive 1863 riot broke out in New York City following an attempt to do this action to provide troops for the Civil War. For ten points, name this often unpopular practice of selecting people to serve in the military.", "answer": "<b><u>Draft</u></b> (accept <b><u>Conscription</u></b>; prompt on descriptive answers including putting people into the military)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "The Lorentz transformation was confirmed by tests of this theory, including the Ives-Stilwell Experiment and the Kennedy-Thorndike Experiment. This theory's development introduced terms into physics such as spacetime and time dilation and helped scientists predict gravitational waves and black holes. For ten points, give this shared name of two interrelated theories by Albert Einstein, divided into \"general\" and \"special\" types, that applies to all physical phenomena in the absence of gravity.", "answer": "<b><u>Relativity</u></b> (accept Special <b><u>Relativity</u></b>; accept General <b><u>Relativity</u></b>)", "metadata": "Science - Physics"}, {}, {"question": "Ganymede, the cup-bearer to Zeus, was the son of this city's founder. This city in Dardania was the site of the Palladium, and its king, Laomedon [[lay-AH-meh-don]], was killed after refusing to give a herd of magical horses to Herakles. Years later, this city was sacked thanks to the trickery of Odysseus, leading to the death of its last king, Priam [[PRY-am]]. Lying near the River Scamander, for ten points, what Anatolian city-state was the subject of a ten-year war fought over a woman named Helen?", "answer": "<b><u>Troy</u></b> (accept <b><u>Troia</u></b>; or <b><u>Truva</u></b>; accept <b><u>Ilium</u></b>; <b><u>Ilion</u></b>; or <b><u>Ilios</u></b>; accept <b><u>Wilusa</u></b>; or <b><u>Truwisa</u></b>)", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {}, {"question": "Transfer of footballers within this entity was the subject of the 1995 Bosman ruling. This entity is derived from an earlier \"Coal and Steel Community\" and was formally established by the 1992 Maastricht Treaty. In 2016, the United Kingdom voted in a referendum to leave this body, an act known as \"Brexit.\" For ten points, name this political and economic association of countries from the namesake continent.", "answer": "<b><u>European Union</u></b> (or <b><u>EU</u></b>)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {}, {"question": "At the urging of Muhammad Ali, this man publicly denounced the Vietnam War in a speech delivered at the Riverside Church in New York City. During this man\u2019s controversial \u201cPoor People\u2019s Campaign,\u201d he went to the Mason Temple to deliver an address entitled \u201cI\u2019ve Been to the Mountaintop.\u201d For ten points, name this first president of the Southern Christian Leadership Conference who delivered a speech on the steps of the Lincoln Memorial, declaring, \u201cI Have a Dream.\u201d", "answer": "Martin Luther <b><u>King</u></b> Jr. (accept <b><u>MLK</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This dynasty established hegemony after Emperor Tang won the Battle of Mingtiao [[MING-TYAO]] during the first \"Noble Revolution\" in East Asian history. This dynasty made its capital the city of Yin, near modern Anyang. During this dynasty, mystics began using turtle shells, or \"oracle bones,\" for divination. Following the Battle of Muye [[MOO-YUH]], the Zhou [[ZHOH]] overthrew, for ten points, what Chinese dynasty, the first with extensive archaeological records?", "answer": "<b><u>Shang</u></b> Dynasty (or <b><u>Sh\u0101ng</u></b>ch\u00e1o; accept <b><u>Yin</u></b> Dynasty or <b><u>Y\u012bn</u></b>d\u00e0i before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "Cassius Dio reported that four of these people were wrongfully executed in a trial brought about by Caracalla on charges of <em>crimen incesti</em> [[KRIH-men in-KEH-stee]]. Emperor Elagabalus [[eh-lah-GAH-bah-lus]] caused controversy after marrying Aquilia Severa, one of these people. The mother of Romulus and Remus, Rhea Silvia, legendarily served as one of these priestesses. For ten points, name these \"Virgin\" priestesses of Rome dedicated to the goddess of the hearth.", "answer": "<b><u>Vestal</u></b> Virgins (accept <b><u>Vestal</u></b>s; or <b><u>Vest\u0101l</u></b>\u0113s; accept <b><u>Priestess of Vesta</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "Early 20th century observers believed this building in the U.S. would collapse by itself, having become known as \"Burnham's Folly\" before construction. This building served as a hub of young publishers as the MacMillan Publishing company rented all 21 stories of this building by the mid 1950s. A contemporary reporter of the <em>New York Tribune</em> called this building \"A stingy piece of pie/the greatest inanimate troublemaker in New York.\" For ten points, name this triangular building which names a neighborhood in Manhattan.", "answer": "<b><u>Flatiron</u></b> Building (accept <b><u>Flatiron</u></b> District)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Architecture"}, {}, {"question": "<b><u>In this election year, unpledged electors from Alabama and Mississippi cast</u></b> <b><u>votes for Harry Byrd in opposition to the Democrats' move away from segregation,</u></b> <b><u>though the Democrats won anyway. For this election, that party nominated their</u></b> <b><u>second (+)</u> Catholic since 1928, choosing a Massachusetts senator who later died at the hands of Lee Harvey Oswald. The first televised presidential debates (*) </b>occurred during, for ten points, what election year in which Richard Nixon was defeated by John F. Kennedy?", "answer": "<b><u>1960</u></b> United States Presidential Election", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>The poor reception of an epic poem titled for this group led to the expulsion of</u></b> <b><u>Apollonius [[ah-poh-LOH-nee-us]] from the isle of Rhodes. At the request of King</u></b> <b><u>Pelias [[peh-LEE-ahs]], this group travelled to the homeland of Medea in (+)</u> the historical Kingdom of Colchis [[KOHL-kiss]]. The warrior who slayed the Minotaur, Theseus, was a member of this group, alongside (*) </b>Meleager and Orpheus. For ten points, name this group led by Jason who set sail to find the Golden Fleece.", "answer": "<b><u>Argonaut</u></b>s (accept <b><u>Argonaut</u></b>ai; accept <b><u>Sailors</u></b> of the <em><b><u>Argo</u></b></em> and equivalents; accept <em><b><u>Argonaut</u></b>ica</em>; prompt on answers such as \"Jason's crew\")", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {"question": "<b><u>In the late 18th century, this U.S. state created a system of five rotating</u></b> <b><u>capitals including East Greenwich [[GREHN-\"itch\"]] and South Kingston. During King</u></b> <b><u>Philip's War, the Great Swamp Fight occurred in this state, resulting in the mass</u></b> <b><u>enslavement of the (+)</u> Narragansett [[nair-ah-GAN-set]] people. This state was first settled by expelled Puritan minister Roger Williams. The colony of Providence Plantations was (*) </b>in, for the point, what modern New England state?", "answer": "State of <b><u>Rhode Island</u></b> (accept its former name, until 2020, the State of <b><u>Rhode</u></b> <b><u>Island</u></b> and Providence Plantations)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>A Christian from this city named Anselm proposed the first ontological</u></b> <b><u>argument in his work</u> </b><em><b><u>Proslogion</u></b></em><b><u> [[proh-SLOH-gee-on]]. Henry the Young King</u></b> <b><u>unknowingly ordered the 1170 execution (+)</u> of a church official from this city. Following the reforms of King Henry VIII [[the eighth]], the spiritual leader of Anglicanism is the archbishop of this city. Thomas \u00e0 Becket served (*) </b>as the archbishop of, for ten points, what English city which names a set of Middle English <em>Tales</em>?", "answer": "<b><u>Canterbury</u></b> (accept Anselm of <b><u>Canterbury</u></b>; accept Archbishop of <b><u>Canterbury</u></b>; accept the <em><b><u>Canterbury</u></b> Tales</em>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This type of government was established following the successive overthrow</u></b> <b><u>of Hippias [[HIP-ee-us]] and the Spartan-favoring oligarchy of Isagoras [[iss- ah-GOH-</u><u>russ]] in favor of Cleisthenes's [[KLYS-thin-eez-is]] reforms. This (+)</u> government style, for which Solon laid the foundations, included a punishment called ostracism, and was available to all citizens, though that excluded women and (*) </b>slaves. For ten points, name this isonomic government style that was adopted by ancient Athens, in which citizens governed themselves directly.", "answer": "Athenian <b><u>Democracy</u></b> (accept <b><u>Demokratia</u></b>; accept <b><u>Democratic</u></b>; prompt on \"Athens\" or \"Demos\"; prompt on descriptive answers)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This man, who advocated for the \"Five Races under One Union\" policy,</u></b> <b><u>incorporated his own Methodist beliefs into his \"New Life Movement.\" This man</u></b> <b><u>perpetrated the April 12th Purge of Communists (+)</u> and other workers led by Zhou Enlai [[ZHOH EN-\"LIE\"]]. This man's National Revolutionary Party formed the United Front with Mao's Red Army to (*) </b>defend against the Japanese. For ten points, name this \"Generalissimo\" of Nationalist China who fled to Taiwan in the 1940s.", "answer": "<b><u>Chiang</u></b> Kai-shek (accept <b><u>Chiang</u></b> Chieh-shih; or <b><u>Jiang</u></b> Jieshi)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b>Albert </b> <b>Einstein </b> <b>proved </b> <b>this </b> <b>statement </b> <b>using </b> <b>dissection </b> <b>without </b> <b><u>rearrangement, and James A. Garfield proved this statement using a trapezoid. For a</u></b> <b><u>Cartesian coordinate plane, the (+)</u> Euclidean distance formula can be derived from this statement. A Babylonian tablet called Plimpton 322 is the oldest known record of (*) </b>\"triples\" derived from this theorem that include examples such as (3,4,5) and (5,12,13). For ten points, what is this formula stated as \"A squared plus B squared equals C squared,\" named from a Greek philosopher?", "answer": "<b><u>Pythagorean</u></b> theorem (or <b><u>Pythagoras's</u></b> theorem; accept <b><u>Pythagorean</u></b> triples; accept \"equation\" in place of \"theorem\")", "metadata": "Science - Other Science - Math"}, {"question": "<b><u>In this year, England returned all continental possessions to the French, save</u></b> <b><u>Calais [[kah-LAY]], in the Peace of \u00c9taples [[eh-TAHPL]]. The Jewish people of Spain</u></b> <b><u>were expelled or forced to convert in the Alhambra Decree (*)</u> of this year, passed by Ferdinand and Isabella. In this year, the settlement of \"La Navidad\" was founded after the ship </b><em><b>Santa Maria</b></em><b> ran aground on Hispaniola. Christopher Columbus unintentionally (*) </b>\"discovered\" the New World in, for ten points, what 15th century year?", "answer": "<b><u>1492</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>General Washington advocated for the John Hancock-led Second Continental</u></b> <b><u>Congress to pass a 1777 inoculation order against this disease for all new recruits to</u></b> <b><u>the Continental Army. During the Siege of Fort Pitt, William Trent likely fabricated an</u></b> <b><u>account of giving blankets ridden (+)</u> with this disease to the Delaware tribe. The World Health Organization announced the 1979 eradication (*) </b>of, for ten points, which disease caused by strains of <em>variola</em>?", "answer": "<b><u>Smallpox</u></b> (accept <em><b><u>variola</u></b></em> major or <em><b><u>variola</u></b></em> minor before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b><u>These people, who subjugated the Avvites, established a so-called</u></b> <b><u>\"Pentapolis,\" a group of five cities built on the Road of Horus, including their cultural</u></b> <b><u>center at Ashkelon. Scholars have speculated that the \"Peleset,\" a (+)</u> subset of the Sea Peoples, are these Semitic people, who were later repopulated in Canaan by Ramesses. King David legendarily (*) </b>defeated, for ten points, what people's champion Goliath in single combat in a Biblical tale?", "answer": "<b><u>Philistine</u></b>s (accept <b><u>Peleset</u></b> before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}